Contact

mwende.njiraini@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/njirainimwende-8a7136b (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Program Management
Project Management
Telecommunications

Languages

English (Full Professional)
Kiswahili (Professional Working)
Kiswahili (Native or Bilingual)

Honors-Awards
Commonwealth Scholarship

Njiraini Mwende

Telecommunications Engineer//Internet Governance Enthusiast// Amateur Photographer// Bird Watcher//Aspiring Pastry Chef

Summary

Mwende Njiraini is a Telecommunication Engineer by profession.

Ms. Njiraini has since 2000 held various positions at the Communications Authority of Kenya, the ICT regulator and is currently a Manager in charge of Type Approval. She has been a faculty member DiploFoundation's Internet Governance Capacity Building Programme (IGCBP).

At the Authority, she has specialized in Internet services regulation making a significant contribution to the licensing of the first Internet Exchange Point (IXP), the publication of the Guidelines on the Implementation and provision of Voice over Internet Protocol (VoIP) Services and the establishment of the Kenya Network Information Centre (KENIC).

As the Mobile Number Portability (MNP) project manager, Mwende lead a working group in the development of the Guidelines for the Provision of Mobile Number Portability (MNP) Services in Kenya, making Kenya the 2nd Sub-Saharan country to successfully launch the service.

Currently, she managing the conformance and interoperability function of the Authority as well as monitoring compliance with the Guidelines for Network Redundancy, Resilience and Diversity for ICT Networks in Kenya.

Mwende has a great interest in Cybersecurity and was a key note speaker at 23rd Annual Forum of Incident Response and Security Teams (FIRST) conference. She is currently represents Kenya at the International Telecommunications Union (ITU-T) Study Group 17: Security and is the Chair of ITU-T Regional Group for Africa (SG17RG-AFR).

She is a member of Nature Kenya, an environmental conservation society and in her spare time teaches children how to bake and decorate cakes with Little Bakers Kenya.

Experience

International Telecommunication Union
Chairman ITU-T SG17 Regional Group for Africa (SG17RG-AFR)
January 2019 - Present (1 year 4 months)
Geneva Area, Switzerland

As Chairman of the ITU-T Study Group 17 Regional Group for the Africa (SG17RG-AFR) my objective is to facilitate development of, access to, implementation of and influence ITU-T security standards for Africa.

Communications Authority of Kenya Telecommunications Engineer April 2000 - Present (20 years 1 month) Nairobi, Kenya

- *Multi-stakeholder project management including:
- (1) Device Management System, 2016
- (2) Redundancy, Resilience and Diversity of Telecommunication Networks in Kenya, 2016
- (3) Mobile Number Portability Project, 2010 –2011
- (4) Kenya Network Information Centre project, 2003 –2004
- (5) Kenyan Telemedicine Project, 2002
- (6) Internet Exchange point (IXP) project, 2000 –2001
- * Research in new and emerging communication technologies and development of appropriate regulatory guidelines:
- (1) Procedures and Guidelines for the Provision of Mobile Number Portability (MNP) Services in Kenya, 2010

- (2) Voice over Internet protocol (VoIP), 2005
- (3) Wireless Fidelity (Wi Fi), 2005
- * Participation and facilitation of development of standards and industry code for existing as well as new technologies and services
- (1) International Telecommunications Union Standardization Sector (ITU-T Study Group 17-Security)
- (2) Kenya Bureau of Standards (KeBS)
- (3) Kenya Accreditation Services (KENAS)
- * Study the environmental impact of existing and new technologies and develop appropriate safeguards
- (1) Evaluation of Environmental Impact Assessment Reports for communication projects to ensure conformance to International Commission on Non-Ionising Radiation Protection (ICNIRP) guidelines, site sharing or colocation and public consultation.
- (2) Environmental of audit of Communication infrastructure to ensure compliance to Code of Practice for the Deployment of Communications Infrastructure in Kenya
- * Internship coordinator, Communications Authority of Kenya, Licensing, Compliance and Standards department.
- * Resource person and representative at local and international conferences including:
- (1) International Telecommunications Union
- (2) Internet Governance Forum (IGF) Athens, Hyderabad, Sharm El Sheikh, Vilinus, and Nairobi
- (3) Kenya national Internet Governance Forum (KIGF) (2008, 2009) and East Africa Internet Governance Forum (EAIGF) (2008, 2009)

DiploFoundation

Tutor, Internet Governance Capacity Building Programme February 2006 - January 2013 (7 years)

Tutoring of participants from the African Region using DiploFoundation collaborative online learning platform on infrastructural, development, social-cultural, economic and legal aspects of Internet Governance, ICT Strategy and supervision of IG-related research projects.

Communicatons Authority of Kenya Mobile Number Portability Project Manager July 2010 - June 2011 (1 year) Nairobi, Kenya

Facilitation of consultations between Mobile Operators in Kenya (Safaricom, Airtel Networks, Essar Telecom and Telkom Orange) and the Porting Access Kenya Limited on the provision of Mobile Number Portability (MNP) services.

Development of the Procedures and Guidelines for the Provision of Mobile Number Portability (MNP) Services in Kenya and the Mobile Number Portability Service Agreement

Coordination of Inter-operator tests and service audit

Commonwealth Telecommunication Organisation Intern

January 2007 - February 2007 (2 months)

Research and development of the Rural Telecommunication Cooperative (Tele-coop)

Kenya Network Information Centre Acting Administrative Manager April 2003 - February 2004 (11 months) Nairobi, Kenya

Responsible for

- Developing mechanisms and strategies for operation and promotion of DOT KE country code Top Level Domain (ccTLD) registry,
- Participating and liaising with regional and international organizations in the formulation and implementation of policies of the Internet core technical and organizational elements in the interest of the Kenyan Internet Community,

- Designing and implementing methodologies to facilitate the public and Kenyan Internet Community participation in ccTLD policy-development procedures,
- Designing and implementing Information Communications Technologies (ICTs) projects in liaison with Local, Regional and International organizations and donor agencies,
- Preparing and presenting reports on the registry's activities to the Board of Directors and,
- Managing the day-to-day running of the registry.

Cadbury Kenya Limited

Sales Administrator

January 1998 - January 2000 (2 years 1 month)

- *Analysis of sales data for reporting to the management
- *Administration of sales order processing and delivery utilizing Sales and Distribution (SD)

module database of the System Application Products (SAP) an Enterprise Integration

Software.

Education

Coventry University

Master of Communications Management with Merit in Business Management, Master of Communications Management · (2003 - 2009)

University of Strathclyde

Masters, Communication Management · (2006 - 2006)

Moi University

Bachelor of Technology, Electrical and Communication Engineering · (1992 - 1998)

Alliance Girls' High School

Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education, High School

Education · (1986 - 1990)